Warren L. Duffield Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Warren L. Duffield papers
1930-1935
MS 2055
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
.67
2 boxes
This collection documents the voyage of the S.S. Jelling in support of the Pan American Airways Expedition of 1933, led by Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, to chart northern air routes to Europe and survey possible landing sites for aircraft on trans-Atlantic flights. Dr. Warren L. Duffield, the medical officer for the expedition, kept a daily log of the voyage, which included stops in Labrador, Greenland, and Iceland. An enthusiatic amatuer photographer, Duffield also took numerous photographs. These materials, and articles written by Dr. Duffield after the voyage, comprise the bulk of the collection. There are also postcards, pamphlets and currency from Greenland and Iceland, some newspaper clippings and articles on the voyage, and a small amount of correspondence.
Duffield, Warren L., 1875-1935
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas Duffield, 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in alphabetical order.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the voyage of the S.S. Jelling in support of the Pan American Airways Expedition of 1933, led by Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh, to chart northern air routes to Europe and survey possible landing sites for aircraft on trans-Atlantic flights. Dr. Warren L. Duffield, the medical officer for the expedition, kept a daily log of the voyage, which included stops in Labrador, Greenland, and Iceland. An enthusiatic amatuer photographer, Duffield also took numerous photographs. These materials, and articles written by Dr. Duffield after the voyage, comprise the bulk of the collection. There are also postcards, pamphlets and currency from Greenland and Iceland, some newspaper clippings and articles on the voyage, and a small amount of correspondence.
Biographical / Historical
Warren L. Duffield was born on Staten Island on February 14, 1875. After graduating from Long Island College Hospital in 1898, he interned at St. John's Hospital and remained there for his subsequent medical career, becoming senior surgeon in 1931. In 1933, he served as the medical officer for the support staff on board the S.S. Jelling with the Pan American Airways Expedition led by Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh. At the end of the voyage, he returned to his work at St. John's Hospital, where he died of a heart attack on November 21, 1935.
Greenland; Iceland; Duffield, Warren L., 1875-1935; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974; Pan American Airways Corporation
- Correspondence
  - Mary M. Duffield
    - To husband, Warren, 1933 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - From Isbrandtsen-Moller Company, 1933 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Warren Duffield
    - "Good Luck" telegrams on departure, 1933 June 27-28 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - From Isbrandtsen-Moller Company, 1933 June 28-30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To wife, Mary, 1933 June 28-August 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - From Vilhjalmur Stefansson, 1933 June-November (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - National Geographic rejection letter, 1933 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - To Anne Lindbergh, 1935 August 22-24 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Journal of voyage on S.S. Jelling, 1933 June 27-September 4
  - Daily journal
    - Handwritten original, with maps (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Typescript, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Log of the S.S. Jelling," extracted from daily journal (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Negatives and photographs, 1933 June 28-September 5
  - Negative album (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photograph album (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, loose (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Newsclippings, 1933 June-December (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Souvenirs
  - Money from Greenland and Iceland, Circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlets from or about Greenland, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Postcards
    - Greenland, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Iceland, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Writings
  - By Duffield
    - "Greenland", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      General
      Submitted to the Explorers Club, New York, 1934 November 26.
    - "Greenland Health Conditions," New York State Journal of Medicine, 1934 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Outline for article on voyage, Circa 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Untitled article, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Scope and Contents
      There are two copies of this article describing the voyage of the S.S. Jelling and the areas visited, one including photographs. It was submitted to the Explorers Club, New York, 1934 November 26.
  - By others
    - Gall, Elaine, "The Lindberghs", 1933 November (Box 2, Folder 9)
      The article is based on an interview with Duffield.
    - Ketchum, W. Q., "The Cruise of the Jelling: With Lindbergh in the North Atlantic," Canadian Aviation, 1934 January (Box 2, Folder 10)